Finding aid to the Senda Berenson papers CA.MS.00037
Smith College Archives
Senda Berenson papers
1892-2006
1897-1915
Smith College Archives
Berenson, Senda, 1868-1954.
CA.MS.00037
2.5 linear feet (4 containers)
Senda Berenson, Smith College's Director of the Gymnasium and Instructor of Physical Culture, introduced the first rules of women's basketball and organized the first women's college basketball game. Her papers contain biographical articles, news clippings, notebooks, correspondence, lecture notes, photographs, and published writings and materials related to her induction into the National Jewish Sports Hall of Fame and other honors.
Biographical / Historical
Senda Berenson, Smith College's Director of the Gymnasium and Instructor of Physical Culture, introduced the first rules of women's basketball and organized the first women's college basketball game. Berenson was born Senda Valvrojenski, March 19, 1868, in Vilna, Lithuania. She trained at the Boston Normal School of Gymnastics and was hired at Smith in January 1892, one month after the game of basketball had been invented by James Naismith at the International YMCA Training School in nearby Springfield, Mass. At Smith, Berenson instituted an program of Swedish gymnastics, which was supplemented by organized athletic contests in sports such as volleyball, fencing, field hockey and basketball, all intended to build character in her female students. She believed in strict and careful supervision of all activities and in offering "the most for the most," i.e., including young women of all skill levels in the program rather than devoting her time to a small group of highly skilled students. This philosophy resulted in a policy at Smith College that favored a strong intramural program over interscholastic athletic competition. Berenson extended her missionary-like work in popularizing Swedish gymnastics beyond Smith, first with students and faculty at Northampton High School, and later with female patients at the Northampton Lunatic Hospital.
Shortly after her appointment at Smith, Berenson read about the new sport of basketball and visited with Naismith to learn more about it. On March 22, 1893, she organized the first women's collegiate basketball game when her Smith freshmen and sophomores played against one another. Influenced by the thinking of her time about women's physical limitations, she soon adapted the rules to avoid the roughness of the men's game. Berenson's rules were first published in 1899. Two years later, she became editor of A. G. Spalding's first Women's Basketball Guide, which further spread her version of basketball for women. In 1985 Berenson and Margaret Wade were the first two women elected to the Basketball Hall of Fame.In 2006 Berenson was inducted into the National Jewish Sports Hall of Fame.
In 1911, after marrying Herbert Vaughan Abbott, a professor of English at Smith, Berenson resigned from her position at the College. She remained as editor of the Women's Basketball Guide and as chair of the U.S. Women's Basketball Committee for six years. Her husband died in 1929. In 1934 she moved to Santa Barbara, Calif. to live with her sister. Berenson died in February 16, 1954.
Scope and Contents
The Senda Berenson papers include biographical articles, news clippings, notebooks, correspondence, lecture notes, photographs, published writings and materials related to her induction into the National Jewish Sports Hall of Fame and other honors. Notable people with whom Berenson corresponded include L. Clark Seelye and Dorothy Ainsworth, as well as several Smith alumnae. Of special importance are Berenson's lecture notes and speeches, which provide insight into her pioneering work on athletics for women, especially basketball.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biography
II. Correspondence, Incoming
III. Correspondence, Outgoing
IV. Lecture Notes
V. Photographs
VI. Writings
Additional Formats
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available on the Web as part of the Five College Archives Digital Access Project.
Related Materials
80. Athletics-Basketball
Agnes Stillman (Smith 1971). "Senda Berenson Abbott: Her Life and Contributions to Smith College and to the Physical Education Profession," thesis for Master of Science degree. May 1971
Dorothy Sears Ainsworth (Smith 1916). "Pioneer in sports for women: Senda Berenson Abbott, 1868-1954," Smith Alumnae Quarterly, May 1954, p. 139.
Senda Berenson. "Exercise cards," Smith College Monthly, October 1899, p. 48.
Senda Berenson. "Health and Fresh Air," Smith College Monthly, October 1901, pp. 62-64.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Senda Berenson Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Basketball--United States--History--Sources.; Berenson, Senda, 1868-1954.; Smith College--Basketball.; Smith College--Faculty.; Smith College--Sports.
- Series I: Biography
  - General: (Box 679, Folder 1)
    - Edith Naomi Hill. "Senda Berenson, Director of Physical Education at Smith College 1892-1911," Research Quarterly, Pioneer Women in Physical Education, pp. 658-65, 1941; Oct
    - Leather-bound notebook of poems and songs
    - News-clippings concerning basketball and theater, 1893-1967
  - Basketball Hall of Fame: (Box 679, Folder 2)
    - News-clipping and program of enshrinement dinner, 1985
    - Correspondence re-induction, 1970-71
  - News-clippings & Physical Training: (Box 679, Folder 3)
    - Elizabeth Paine. "Physical Training at Women's Colleges - Smith," The Illustrated Sporting News, pp. 3-4, 17, 1904; June 4
    - "College Girl from West Better Athlete than Eastern Sister", 1907; Feb 10
    - "A Pioneer in Swedish Gymnastics in the U.S.A.," Husmodern (with transcript translation), 1922
  - Capsule biography for thesis by Agnes Stillman (Smith '71), 1971; May (Box 679, Folder 4)
  - National Jewish Sports Hall of Fame proclamations and other materials, 2006 (Box 680.2)
- Series II: Correspondence, Incoming
  - Baldwin, Ruth (Bowles), n. d. (Box 679, Folder 5)
  - Binyon, Laurence, n. d. (Box 679, Folder 6)
  - Bridges, Robert, 1900 (Box 679, Folder 7)
  - Brooks, Phillips, n. d. (Box 679, Folder 8)
  - Burton, Marion LeRoy, 1911 (Box 679, Folder 9)
  - Campbello, Salone di, n. d. (Box 679, Folder 10)
  - Carmen, Bliss, n. d. (Box 679, Folder 10a)
  - Gardner, Isabella, 1911; May 28 (Box 679, Folder 11)
  - Hill, J. R., 1904; Oct 5 (Box 679, Folder 12)
  - Hitchcock, E., 1908; n. d. (Box 679, Folder 13)
  - Holden, Frances Steele (Smith '19), 1934; Jun 22 (Box 679, Folder 14)
  - Marks, Josephine Peabody, 1910; Apr 10 (Box 679, Folder 15)
  - St. Louis Exposition, 1904; Dec 3 (Box 679, Folder 16)
  - Seelye, L. Clark, 1897-1911 (Box 679, Folder 17)
  - Thompson, Helen E., 1919; Jun 11 (Box 679, Folder 18)
- Series III: Correspondence, Outgoing
  - Ainsworth, Dorothy Sears, 1952 (Box 679, Folder 19)
  - Grierson, Margaret (Storrs) (Smith '22), 1947-53 (Box 679, Folder 20)
  - Miss Mitchell, 1897; Mar 1 (Box 679, Folder 21)
  - Seamans, Dorothy (Smith '14), n. d. (Box 679, Folder 22)
  - Sleeper, Henry Dike, n. d. (Box 679, Folder 23)
  - Miss Spencer, 1911; Feb 15 (Box 679, Folder 24)
  - True, Moses, 1906; Dec 11 (Box 679, Folder 25)
- Series IV: Lecture Notes
  - Basketball rules, posture, self control, and health, 1905-06 (Box 679, Folder 26)
- Series V: Photographs
  - Face, 1897; n. d. (Box 679, Folder 27)
  - Profile, 1897; n. d. (Box 679, Folder 28)
  - Groups, 1897; n. d. (Box 679, Folder 29)
  - Dressed in Gym Suit, 1892-95; n. d. (Box 679, Folder 30)
  - Standing, 1897-1950's (Box 679, Folder 31)
- Series VI: Writings
  - Senda Berenson. "The Significance of Basketball for Women," Basketball for Women, edited by Senda Berenson, pp. 31-46, 1903 (Box 680, Folder 32)
  - Spalding's Official Basket Ball Guide for Women, edited by Senda Berenson, 1913 (Box 680, Folder 33)
  - Speeches:, 1915; n. d. (Box 680, Folder 34)
    - Basketball for Women, notes
    - Necessity of Sleep, notes
    - Physical Training, text
    - Working Girls, notes
  - Speech notes, typed copy (Box 680, Folder 35)
- Books (Box 680.1)